Just to recap some of what we learned back in the foreword.
V.M. Stracca is the name used by an unknown author who wrote 19 books before his supposed death in 1946.
The first was called A Miracle at Braxenholm, published in 1911,
and the last was this novel, Ship of Theseus, published after V.M.S. died by his translator and confident, F.X. Caldera.
Much of what the world knows about Stracca are only rumours, including lists of politically motivated crimes he may have been involved in.
Caldera provides us with a list of the most popular theorised candidates in the foreword,
so let's take a look at this group of characters.
Even from a passing glance, some of these suspects seem more believable than others.
Florence Stonem Smith, for one, is probably a no.
Juan Blas Colverubius, called the last Spanish pirate by some, and almost certainly fictional by Caldera,
is referenced in a couple of footnotes and also in Ship of Theseus itself,
but these seem more like an in-joke between Philo and Stracca.
Apis Amenuensis.
This refers to a real theory that the leader of the Black Hand Gang had a mysterious Iago-like aide
who influenced the decision to assassinate Franz Ferdinand II.
Within S, some people think this could be Stracca,
but we believe this relies on misinterpreting the interlude of Ship of Theseus,
and besides, it's just another pseudonym.
So, with those out the way, it's time to talk about the S organisation.
As mentioned earlier, it was Desjardins who originally came up with the theory
that there may have existed a secret organisation of writers called the S,
consisting of many Stracca candidates.
Really, the biggest evidence for this is that some suspects are clearly the basis
for a group of characters featured in Ship of Theseus.
Their appearances apparently match, and they all have bird-inspired names,
which share the language with the candidates' nationalities.
Thus, whether or not one of them is Stracca, they are significant.
So, let's do a quick round-up.
First, the oldest of the bunch, Torsten Ekström.
A rather successful Swedish author of children's books,
he's automatically a suspect because Summersby named him
the co-author of Miracle at Braxenholm in the Summersby tape.
Obviously, Summersby could have been lying,
but Desjardins firmly believed that Ekström was involved in the S,
even if he doubted he was Stracca.
Also, he is the fourth person to die suspiciously falling from a balcony,
dying in 1931.
In fact, it was from Hotel des deux Martres,
the same hotel as Desjardins.
On page 161, we find out that Ekström was apparently in good spirits,
of vigorous mind, and about to return to work after a bad illness.
At the scene, authorities found a sheet of paper
with hundreds of anagrams written on it in many different languages,
including ones Ekström did not speak.
Next up is Amarante Durand, the only female candidate.
She wrote at least one novel, but made her name as an archaeologist.
She famously discovered a cave in the Dordogne containing ancient paintings,
which is referenced in Chapter 4 of Ship of Theseus.
Her and Ekström's character analogues in Ship of Theseus are unmarried lovers,
and evidence points to this being true in life as well.
On page 217, we get confirmation that Ekström visited her in Egypt in 1921,
and, as we'll soon see, they often met other S members as a pair.
After his death, she moved to Spain and threw herself into various work,
including suffrage, labour protests, and spying in the lead-up to the Spanish Civil War.
It's the latter that got her killed,
as it's mentioned earlier that Durand was shot by Franco's troops near Madrid in 1937.
Although, interestingly, she may have been thrown from a roof first, adding to the pattern.
We also know Durand was rumoured to be close to VMS.
FXC seems to dislike Durand for this reason,
but whether there's actually any merit to her jealousy, we'll judge later.
Segwaying nicely, we have Tiago García Ferrara.
Out of the candidates, Tiago has both the saddest life and biggest fall from grace.
Eric tells us within the first few chapters that he sold out to the fascists,
and on page 173, that's explained.
After fighting on the Republican side of the Spanish Civil War for years,
Ferrara turned coat and sold out Durand in order to protect his family.
They had been friends, too, writing to each other regularly in the 1930s.
However, even without knowing more about this incident, it's hard not to feel bad for Tiago.
He was outcast from society after the war, which coincided with the death of his son.
FXC describes him as very sensitive, and he lived with a shattered heart,
becoming depressed and eventually hanging himself.
So this Spanish incident was bad all round.
Completely uninvolved in this was Reinhold Feuerbach.
The last of the four candidates who have clear ship of Theseus counterparts.
On paper, we know the least about him, but he does seem the most overtly political of the bunch,
being described as an anarchist and polemicist above anything else.
He's about the same age as Ekstrom, so older than the others,
and it's suggested that he may have been involved in the 1886 Haymarket bombing,
i.e. one of the events VMS was accused of.
Most of the information we get about him is from a German magazine article Eric tells us about.
In 1937, he was living in Germany, supported by anarchist groups who revered him for Haymarket,
but soon fled the Nazis to Dublin, where he died in 1940 after a fall in his home.
The only other thing we know is that for decades he travelled with a man called Horst Weschler.
He was described as his secretary and protege.
To a non-historian, it may seem more likely they were lovers, and Eric concurs.
Upon Foyback's death, Weschler said about the Stracca identity rumours,
if there were answers inside him, those answers are gone.
Very helpful.
Alright, so if you've been paying a superhuman amount of attention so far,
you'll notice that all these four died before the novels were finished,
except for the heavily traumatised Ferrara.
However, the same is not true for the last two major candidates.
First up is someone we've already mentioned, Victor Martin Summersby.
Summersby was a popular pulp novelist and screenwriter whose work Eric and Jen both enjoy.
He not only has the initials VMS, but is the only American of the bunch,
and many of the settings and influences of Stracca's novels apparently seem American,
though Shippetheseus does not.
FXC says he was the only friend of VMS's that she knew well,
which both ties him to this group well, also kind of ruling him out Stracca-wise.
Although Summersby doesn't have a proper character in Shippetheseus,
there is a little nod to him in Chapter 10.
An old sailor who looks identical to him in the 1940s.
Our last big name is arguably the most canonically popular candidate,
Guthrie McInnes.
We don't hear much about McInnes from Jarek until after the 200-page mark,
aside from there being a very well-funded group supporting his authorship,
and mentioning he was good at spreading the money around.
Eventually, though, we get a small biography from Eric on page 225.
McInnes was a philosophy wunderkind,
one of Oxford's youngest dons and then a well-known television figure.
He wrote a number of books, but Eric says his radicalism faded with age.
His trademark philosophy is something called multitudinalism,
but this is hard to judge independently because it's only mentioned when Eric and FXC make fun of it.
It seems to argue there is no such thing as a true self and art cannot be made with just one vision,
but Eric claims if there's no real self, there's no moral responsibility,
so you can just do whatever you want, which is telling.
FXC was also adamant that McInnes's nihilism is in strict opposition to Stracka's tangible yearning for meaning.
Jen describes McInnes's novel, A Swindle of Cowbirds,
as a thinly veiled hatchet job on writers he knew, i.e. other candidates.
So overall, he's the kind of guy nothing bad ever happened to.
Jerk.
And indeed, McInnes died peacefully of old age in 1969, unlike the others.
The only other candidate to mention is not on this list, but is named in the foreword.
Vaclav Stracka.
Not to state the obvious, but that guy's name is Stracka.
FXC mentions Vaclav mostly to rule him out,
as his biography starts with him being born in 1892 in South Bohemia,
and ends with him committing suicide in Prague in 1910.
So that's unfortunate.
Despite this, we do get more information about Vaclav in a chapter 3 footnote,
plus a newspaper insert about his death.
These clarify that he was a young, ill-educated factory worker.
He jumped off the Charles Bridge,
and despite someone apparently trying to rescue him,
there was no signs he survived.
Another worker says he jumped due to being turned down by a girl,
although Eric thinks this could be a lie.
There are some suspicious details.
Vaclav had fallen under the influence of syndicalists,
and he was trying to distribute literature even right before the jump.
Furthermore, he may have wanted to be a writer.
Some people, including Moody, claim that even if he did survive,
VMS couldn't possibly be Vaclav because of his little education.
But this is a bad argument,
possibly a reference by Dorst to the Shakespeare authorship debate.
Equally, though, we can't just say,
well, since Shakespeare is Shakespeare, then Stracka must be Stracka.
These are all interesting details, but alone, it's still a stretch.
Aside from the complexities of faking your own death with witnesses,
how does someone go from here to starting a publishing company?
It could be one of these writers just took this young dead radical's name as a pseudonym,
like a martyr.
Now, it's recognised that some of these people definitely knew each other.
Ekstrom and Durand, and Durand and Ferrara.
Feuerbach and Weschler seem separate, since they weren't even novelists.
But there's a well-known photo from 1937,
which features Durand, Ferrara, Weschler,
and a person turned away from the camera.
Immediately, if Weschler was there, then Ferrara probably was too,
so there's another connection.
But is this other person Ferrara, or perhaps VMS?
Currently, we have three options.
One, one of these people was Stracka.
Two, they all worked together as the S organisation to create Stracka's books.
And three, Stracka is someone else,
who was either part of this S organisation or knew all of them separately.
None of the candidates fit perfectly with being VMS,
based on only the info so far.
Most were not alive early or late enough.
For now, let's take a look at number two,
and imagine that they were somehow all involved.
After all, Somersby did claim to co-write the first VMS-attributed book with Ekstrom,
and it's mentioned several times that these novels vary drastically
in prose style, philosophy, and genre.
VMS wrote 19 books,
helpfully listed here on the inside cover.
Are there any which seem more connected to a specific candidate?
Yes.
Eric says that both Night Palisades and The Santana March have similarities to Somersby's prose,
and The Santana March getting a film adaptation also fits his work.
A couple of the other novels have obvious plot connections to the Stracka candidates.
The blurb of The Square matches Farback and The Haymarket Massacre,
and The Painted Cave has details that can only come from Durand.
Triptych of Mirrors is apparently the worst and most disjointed Stracka book,
in a way that resembles McInnes.
Which is strange, because McInnes is one of the most plausible Stracka candidates dates-wise,
but this seems to be his only VMS novel.
100 Aprils and Amritsar also has a clear author, but we'll come back to that,
and likewise for Washington and Green, which has an almost identical structure.
As for the others, though, those don't have an obvious author.
Eric describes the Black 19 as an outlier,
with not much overlap in material or style with other VMS books.
Some books are only mentioned in one or two footnotes and don't mention plot details,
and Hanging the Dead isn't mentioned at all, so who knows for those.
The final three Stracka books prior to Ship of Theseus are mentioned quite frequently,
but nothing obviously lines up.
These all seem to share more elements with Ship of Theseus than with other novels,
especially Coriolis.
And of course, there's the very first, Miracle at Braxenholm,
which we also can't attribute yet,
although Eric thinks the tone is pretty young-sounding.
Unfortunately, since Ekstrom didn't normally write for adults,
and we're missing details about his life,
it's very hard to guess what he may have been involved with,
even though context suggests he must have had a hand in something.
So all these individual ties further the idea that the candidates work together,
but it doesn't explain how this all started and why.
And ultimately, it doesn't matter hugely if the books were co-written or not,
because that doesn't identify who Caldera Stracka was,
the person writing to her all this time,
the one who wrote Ship of Theseus after most of the others were dead.
So who was this person?
Well, we have lots of proof of who it can't be.
In the yellow-green phase,
Jen comes up with the idea of comparing different members' handwriting
to notes in the original Miracle at Braxton Home manuscript,
which Eric has pictures of.
They're able to rule out Ekstrom, Durand, Ferrara, and Feuerbach.
So already, there must have been another who wrote the first novel.
Remember the Hotel Florida photo?
In Ferrara's personal papers,
Jen finds a letter from V. Finch,
dated 30th October 1937.
V. Finch is probably Somersby,
given the initial and bird-used.
So this rules out everyone named in the photo
and Somersby as not being VMS.
Speaking of secrecy,
why exactly does VMS need to stay secret anyway?
Well, turns out his eat-the-rich mentality
and penchant for uprisings makes very powerful enemies.
Not just governments,
but people whose wealth and influence could topple civilizations.
Reintroducing Hermes Bouchard,
the villain of S.
You may remember us mentioning the pre-Bouchard.
Well, that stunt started a lifelong rivalry.
Bouchard inspired antagonists in both Wineblood's Mine
and Ship of Theseus.
He owned some kind of company that dissolved post-World War I
and lived in an estate of unknown location.
So here's the issue.
That monkey that Straca sent actually had a note pinned to it.
While newspapers at the time reported it simply reading
that Straca didn't like prizes,
Caldeira claims it was an accusation towards Bouchard.
Specifically, that he had orchestrated the deaths
of syndicalist agitators
and was behind a recent massacre of factory workers in Calais.
This is described by FXC in Chapter 4.
After the Calais massacre,
authorities declared that the bomb had been fashioned
from explosives stolen from the Bouchard factory.
This was, to a degree, true.
They'd been stolen from the factory
by workers encouraged to do so
by an agent who'd infiltrated their camp.
The agent then stole the dynamite back from them
and because it was traceable to the workers,
Bouchard's thugs were free to use it to do their worst,
with little risk of Bouchard's plans being discovered.
Eric says Straca's note was in Munich
until it disappeared in 1983 and quotes it.
You seek a world populated by trick monkeys
who dance to your tunes for the empty promise of coins.
Jen and FXC both seemed to agree
that this accusation defined the rest of Straca's life.
And when Eric met FXC,
she confirmed that everything goes back to Calais.
If this is true,
Bouchard might also be our most likely suspect
for the Santorini man murders.
This was at least Desjardins' theory.
But how exactly would Bouchard have that much influence
if his company ended?
Well, it kind of didn't.
It just went on to spawn and control
a bunch of shell companies,
creating quite a legacy in Jerick's present.
A particular footnote cipher
reveals one of these shells
is a Dutch weapons manufacturer
called Arp Syndicate.
They are not publicly connected,
but the first chairman of Arp was A.R. Prinsen,
a man who previously worked for Bouchard
at the Calais factory during 1912.
And that's not all about Arp.
In Ship of Theseus itself,
the Bouchard stand-in,
called Vevoda,
is working on some kind of strange
and frightening weapon.
And footnote 10 of chapter 4
suggests that both Caldera and Straca
thought that Bouchard was also.
Caldera believes including this information
in Ship of Theseus is dangerous,
which probably explains why she went into hiding.
Jen discovers evidence for this theory.
In February 1946,
there were reports of strange
indigo-coloured flashes in the sky
near the Dutch town of Volfica,
where the Arp Syndicate had a factory.
And there were accounts of weird smells
at the Calais-Bouchard factory
before the massacre,
which is also referenced in Ship of Theseus.
But Bouchard and the S both died decades ago.
Why would the Santorini man murders occur
until the 70s,
and why reappear now?
This is a great question we will return to.
For now, it's implied that Hermes Bouchard
had a son possibly creating an heir.
And Bouchard's wife killed herself
a month after the awards ceremony,
which might give all the Bouchards
a more personal grudge against Straca.
Going back to Straca, though,
in the yellow-green phase
while tracing Bouchard's companies,
Jen makes the most important series of findings
in the whole book.
First of all,
both that article describing Feuerbach
and the interview about Václav Straca's death
were in magazines owned by Bouchard.
But more importantly,
on October 30th, 1910,
the same day as the Prague Bridge Jump,
the names Stenfok, Corbeau,
and a Czech, Guest,
are registered in the nearby Hotel Volieri.
The next day,
the names Pfeiffer and Ostrero join,
and it's also confirmed
that the former was travelling with his secretary.
This is therefore huge,
the earliest and only record we have
of all these people meeting.
Plus, who could this guest be
except an alive Václav Straca?
If so,
Václav would be an untraceable man
with no connections
other than to this group of writers.
His candidacy now works on multiple levels.
We've been avoiding the novel so far
since we'll get back to it later,
but the plot of Ship of Theseus
makes far more sense
when viewed as a reflection of Václav's life
being in the S-organisation.
For context,
the first four chapters
consist of
an unnamed protagonist
being reborn from a river,
meeting a group of sheer names
with the birds in this hotel register,
and witnessing a massacre
of striking workers
organised by an evil factory owner.
Seems pretty cut and dry.
Václav would also have been
the best option for Caldeira,
which she herself admits to Eric.
He was the youngest of the main candidates,
though still older than Caldeira,
and the most free to run away with her
if he chose.
So, from this point onwards,
Jen and Eric form a new theory.
The news article said that
Václav was holding his manuscript
when he jumped.
One of the few things we know about Ekstrom
is that he was a great swimmer at university.
What if Ekstrom is the one
who dove after Václav
and succeeded in saving him?
Then he and Durand bring him to the hotel
after noticing his soggy manuscript pages.
In fact, what if those pages
became the first novel,
The Miracle at Braxenholm?
Consider this possible timeline.
Durand and Ekstrom
save a young radical
who has a broken heart
and a book he needs help reconstructing.
They decide to take him under their wing
and invite their like-minded friends
to meet him too,
so Václav suddenly has a community.
Then, after Braxenholm is published
and becomes a sensation,
the group realises that
maybe they can use Václav's anonymity
to make political statements
they otherwise couldn't
as VMS.
If any of these people
were at the Calais Massacre
and Chapter 3 of Ship Athysius
suggests Václav himself
could have been,
then trying to expose Bouchard
would be a great place to start.
As to why Václav went along
with all this,
who knows?
Maybe he felt indebted
to Ekstrom and Durand.
Maybe he was excited
to be a proper writer.
FXC thought Václav
was in love with Durand,
but an entry in Ekstrom's diary
from May 1929
suggests that the relationship
was more paternal.
Our friend has become
more like a son to me
than I ever thought possible.
A feels similarly.
Grateful.
For what it's worth,
Eric does think that all the books
share a consistent vision,
one person's rage at the world
and love of the written word.
So if he's right,
that person could be Václav,
having a hand in all the novels
as the organisation's hidden face.
The theory Jen and Eric
seem to settle on
is that the others
co-wrote all the books
except the last three.
The love story of Winged Shoes,
the messy search for identity
in Coriolis,
and the guilty and mournful
protagonist of Ship of Theseus,
who watches his friends die
one by one.
Here's the rub, though.
This is all really speculation.
Jen and Eric don't have much proof.
They know that these S members,
let's call them the original S,
all met before Braxton Home was published.
But we need more evidence
of what happened next.
Well, in the yellow-green phase,
Jen emails a museum
dedicated to Durand
and surprisingly,
gets a bunch of documents back.
These include excerpts
from Durand's diaries,
which give other examples
of S members meeting up.
On 31st of October 1921,
Ekstrom, Durand,
and Guthrie McInnes
all have dinner together
in Alexandria
while Durand is on a dig,
which we can guess
is when he was first invited in.
McInnes and Summers Bay
are probably the two
most important figures
in the S-Org's
second generation,
so to speak.
But Eric also casually names
quite a number of other
possible members
on page 268.
Sing is the only relevant one,
as he's confirmed
in another Durand diary entry
from January 1st, 1922.
She mentions meeting
with all the old pseudonyms
plus new ones.
Saras,
Hindi for Stork,
so Sing,
Pierich,
Scottish Gaelic for Parrot,
possibly Guthrie McInnes,
Finch,
Summers Bay,
and Swan,
unknown,
possibly Lewis Looper.
Sing is also likely
the co-author
for 100 Aprils of Amritsar
and helped influence
Washington and Green,
as Eric claims
his style and themes
are similar,
so we can add him
to our authors list.
Although this all
seems to be going swimmingly,
the S must have fallen apart
at some point.
From early on,
we get mentions
of a new S
and hints that
one or more members
sold out the original group.
If you've been paying attention,
you might assume
this is a reference
to the Ferrara-Durand betrayal,
but Jen and Eric
specifically mention McInnes.
So what happened?
Here's where
Caldera's ciphers
finally come in.
Through these,
we learn of three betrayals
that VMS himself
seemingly didn't know about,
which helped cause
the downfall
of the S organization.
First off,
the Chapter 2
footnote cipher
gives the phrase
Looper Agent.
This one is complicated.
Jen and Eric
say Looper split
from the S in 1926,
which means
he must have been
a real guy
and not just VMS.
But to complicate matters further,
Eric says this
on page 308.
Maybe Looper
and the Amanuensis
had scrubbed
slash secret histories.
The second,
far more pressing
cipher revelation
is in Chapter 6
when FXC
tries to tell
Stracca
that
Mac was Judas,
not Tiago.
In other words,
McInnes is the one
who betrayed Durand.
Ferrara disappeared
a few days
before her death,
so everyone assumed
it was him.
But nope,
the poor guy
was set up.
This has ramifications
not just on the past,
but the present too,
as Jen finds out
for the last 10 years,
Professor Moody
has been receiving
funding from
the McInnes Foundation
via the aptly named
Caledonian Society
for Literature.
When Eric visits Caldera,
she tells him more
about her interactions
with McInnes.
Apparently,
he fancied himself
as a Casanova type
who could swoon
any woman
with a bottle of wine,
a trick he tried
on both FXC
and Durand
to poor results.
It doesn't seem unlikely,
given everything else
about him,
that McInnes might have
resented their rejections,
and that's partly why
he didn't hesitate
to target them both.
In early 1946,
though,
McInnes visited Caldera
once again in New York,
claiming that he
desperately needed
to get in touch
with the real Straca
and tried to bribe her.
Although obviously
she said she didn't know,
she always wondered
afterwards if she could
have accidentally
given him something
he could use.
Now,
you might be wondering,
why did McInnes not know
how to contact Straca himself?
Jen and Eric wonder
the same thing
on page 293.
Eric theorises
that perhaps the only people
who knew his true identity
were the original members.
However,
Jen mentions that
Somersby did seem
to have met him too
based on his letters.
Either way,
clearly everyone
who did know
kept it a secret
even among the S.
It's worth mentioning,
by the way,
during Eric's meeting
with FXC,
he shows her
the Somersby tape
and she becomes emotional.
She thinks Somersby
probably confessed,
so McInnes' S
would leave her alone.
The last big cipher
revelation involves
another sidelined
member of the S,
Horst Wexler.
The chapter 3 cipher
translates to
ARP is Bouchard
is HW.
This is how Jen
connects the ARP
syndicate company
to Bouchard,
but what about HW?
Eric says that
if it meant
Horst Wexler,
then VMS
was in real danger.
But sure enough,
the pieces add up.
Jen finds a record
of Wexler
as a passenger
on a ship
leaving Dublin
for Liverpool
one week
before Feuerbach
was killed.
The ship vanished
somewhere over the water,
but Eric later says
HW lived.
It turns out
an H. Wexler
entered Rotterdam
in June 1940
and subsequently vanished.
But then in a photo
of the ARP
syndicate board
of directors,
there is a man
called Gernot Klein
who looks exactly
like Wexler.
Did Wexler
leave Dublin
because he knew
Feuerbach was going
to be targeted?
Why would he
sell him out
after decades?
The answer seems
to be for money
and success.
Wexler was
the only original
S member
who wasn't a writer.
He apparently
wrote some dispatches
for small Spanish
anarchist publications
and was writing
a novel,
but it never got published.
However,
FXC says that
in 1940
she received
a manuscript
sent from Dublin
that was far worse
quality than
VMS's usual
manuscripts.
It was in English
but with spelling mistakes
that seemed like
a native German speaker
wrote it,
and VMS later
asked for it back
so he could destroy it.
Perhaps this was Wexler
and the rejection
left him open
to being tempted
by Bouchard.
At ARP
he had power
and influence
and respect
which he may not
have gotten
from the other
S members.
So just to recap,
over the course
of 15 years
all the original
members of the S
were either
bought by Bouchard
or killed
with the exception
of Vaclav.
The timeline we have
is thus.
Looper disappears
in 1926,
Ekstrom dies
in 1931,
Durand dies
and Ferraro's
outcast in 1937,
Horst Wexler
disappears
and Feuerbach
dies in 1940,
Vaclav dies in 1946,
Summersby dies
in 1951.
Sources conflict
about McInnis.
Desjardins' notes
suggest he left
S in 1964
but Summersby said
it was much earlier,
pre-1951
but he must have
been turned
before 1937
and could have been
as early as 1930.
Jen also mentions
Singh was alive
by the 1940s.
This decline
is sad to see
and seems to have
affected Vaclav as well.
FXC reports
he felt like
the last of his kind.
So that basically
brings us to present day
but still doesn't
explain it.
As Jarek says
on page 396,
people are still
going missing,
falling,
getting Santorini-manned
so someone's
out there fighting.
Hope the S is
because the new S is.
Eric also says,
a lot of things
that look like
they're S
or new S related
are happening
all of a sudden.
What if all of that
isn't over?
What if it went dormant
but now it's coming back?
Let's discuss
one of these
present day victims
for a moment,
our old friend Desjardins.
He seems awfully
well informed,
doesn't he?
He certainly theorised
more accurately
than every other researcher.
Turns out
Jean B had a big secret.
During the secret dinner
Eric attended in Paris,
someone referred to Desjardins
as a widower
and other students
responded by
immediately shutting them down.
In the purple-red phase,
Eric discovers
that Desjardins
indeed married a woman
called Signé Rab
in Carcassonne
in 1952.
This is wild
because that name
is in Ship of Theseus,
added by FXC
to the interlude
as a direct question
to Straga.
Who is Signé Rab?
On the wedding invitation,
we see that
Signé's date of birth
is listed as
4th of November 1930
and her mother
as A. Rab.
Rab is apparently
German for raven,
matching the pseudonym
Corbeau.
So,
logic detates
A. Rab
is Amarante Durand
and Signé
is Durand's daughter.
We have two sources
which corroborate this.
In October 1930,
Somersby wrote
a letter to Ekstrom
saying he was
distressed to hear
of A's lengthy
hospital exile,
perhaps a rough
pregnancy for Durand.
Then in November,
Ekstrom writes
in his diary
that his friend
visits him
and he finds it hard
not to weep openly,
weeping with joy
to see his daughter
and surrogate son
together perhaps?
Now,
apparently some S-fans
believe Durand
and Vaclav
were involved romantically
and Signé is his daughter,
which we do not.
But FXC clearly
shares their concern.
Eric brought up
her question when they met
before he knew
about Desjardins' marriage
and she says
she only knew the name
because McInnis
mentioned it
in their meeting.
Personally,
I'd still argue
it's insane
for Caldeira to write
Who is Signé Rab
directly into
Ship of Theseus
when Bouchard agents
are actively tracking
down anyone
connected with the S.
But she apparently
assumed it was Durand
and never found out
otherwise.
Ironically though,
FXC did meet Desjardins.
In fact,
he was who gave her
the final pages
of Ship of Theseus.
Alongside that package
sent to Jarek,
she recounts
how a French man
moving with great sadness
delivered them to her
in the mid-70s.
Turns out,
Signé died in 1956
after a long illness,
which we don't learn
until page 434.
This tragedy
adds to Desjardins' motivations
and could explain
why he fell out
with Moody
because the latter
started getting funding
from McInnis,
the guy who orphaned Signé.
Like McInnis,
Moody places money
and fame
before honesty
and loyalty.
Hence,
Desjardins knew
he could trust Eric
as someone
who wasn't in league
with Moody
and didn't have
any connection
to his money.
Back to Signé though,
where did this poor kid
go in the 1930s
after both her parents
died?
We do get an answer.
That lawyer's daughter
tells Eric a story
about a little girl
with no parents
who was chased
around the world
by bad people
and had two uncles
who took turns
being her dad.
Given the context,
one of these uncles
must have been
Summersby
and although we're
speculating,
we think the other
is Vaclav.
Everyone is dead
at this point
apart from him
and newer members
like Sing
but no one else
was as close
to Ekstrom and Durand
or as able
to keep Signé a secret.
This would help
explain a few
outstanding questions.
Firstly,
when recording his tape,
Summersby wasn't
just trying to protect
his friend FXC,
he was also
protecting Signé.
He was obviously
trapped with agents
on board
and maybe he thought
it would convince them
that the S was over.
Summersby is absolutely
the best S member
for the record.
Additionally,
Vaclav being Signé's
guardian gives him
more reason to postpone
meeting with Caldeira.
He could have been
worried about risking
Signé for selfish gain.
After all,
Summersby was friends
with her too
but never told
so perhaps he and Vaclav
swore secrecy.
On the downside,
this would mean that
Signé lost all four
parental figures
before dying young herself.
A very sad life
but clearly treasured
by Desjardins.
We're coming to the end
of this section now,
having covered all the details
we can gain from the footnotes
and notes in S.
However,
as you've probably noticed,
there are a number of details
we haven't made sense of yet,
listed here.
Some of these
we will get insight into
from the novel
and others we won't
but we will do our best
to address each of them.
For now though,
let's tackle one of the very
first mysteries raised.
Did Stracca really die in Havana?
It's not a very exciting answer
but there's essentially
no evidence that he didn't.
His assumed defenestration
lines up with all other
S-related deaths
and one would think
if he did survive
then there would be some trace
but he doesn't reach out
to FXC,
Signé or Summersby
as the chapter 7 footnotes show
Some losing hope,
please get in touch.
But FXC didn't give up hope
for a long time
as we see through her ciphers.
The chapter 1 code
solved on page 27
spells out
Argosé every 19th
1900 hours
Meeting instructions
for Vaclav
and then the chapter 5 cipher
gives the message
We'll wait 10 years then home
which is what she does.
A couple of additional footnotes
remind him where home is
essentially inviting him
to come seek safety
in L'Ansois
Yet without him doing so
we are left to wonder
whether Vaclav
ever returned Caldera's love.
Eric and Jen
both think she may have been
too committed
considering the lack
of evident reciprocation
he was her whole life
for decades.
Vaclav seems like
a complicated man
and the only insight
we have into his
true feelings and thoughts
is Shepethesius.
So it's finally time
to see what we can learn
from the novel
get some sense of closure
and understand
what it was truly like
to be VMS.