With all this in mind, deciding where to begin is quite a conundrum.
Not least because S actually begins before the beginning, on the inside cover page of
Ship of Theseus.
How we're going to structure this essay is go layer by layer.
There are three different narratives in this book, all of which intertwine.
The first is the handwritten notes, which are set in the present day of 2012.
The second layer is the mystery of VMStraka that the annotators are trying to solve, including
all the historical events and people they learn about, which are fictional to us but
real within the world of S, i.e. the book as a whole.
This historical narrative mostly takes place from the 1910s to the 1950s.
Then the last layer is the Ship of Theseus novel itself, supposedly published in 1949.
This is its own narrative, but also links to the historical layer, so it makes sense
to discuss last.
Layer one is technically the most straightforward, but all these notes are non-chronological.
Part of the fun of this book is deciding how to even tackle reading it, but this does mean
some readers will struggle to follow everything.
So, in this first part, we wanted to re-chronologise this outermost narrative and explain everything
that happens to our two narrators in order.
We will only discuss the Straka mystery elements when it's necessary to understand for context,
because otherwise all the names and dates will get lost very quickly.
We will try to emphasise which details are most important to remember, but just to warn
you, this is a lot of information to cover even within this layer.
Until we can really dive into analysis later, buckle in.
First though, let's cover from the first page up to the end of the foreword, because
this sets up the main Straka mystery and our important present-day characters.
An undergrad literature student finds Ship of Theseus while shelving the library of Pollard
State University.
It says to return to workroom B19, which is assigned to a Mr. Thomas Chadwick and seemingly
has a few of his notes written in the margins.
She's curious enough to read the book, loves it, and writes the owner a message.
He's at first annoyed that she would write on his book, in pen no less, but then she
starts sharing her thoughts.
The two begin passing the book between them, making notes in the margins and leaving it
on a specific shelf for the other to find.
We quickly learn that the undergrad is called Jen and is in her final semester.
She also works as an assistant in the main library, hence the shelving.
The other writer is a bit guarded at first.
He says he's been studying Straka for 12 years, since high school, and is seven years
into a PhD, but claims he'll never get it because of his former supervisor, one professor,
Moody.
Writer number two calls Moody a liar and a thief, and says he is racing the clock before
the latter cashes in on his work.
We don't know what this means yet, but Moody is apparently close to publishing something,
because he recently signed into the library archive with some big New York editor.
Now, it doesn't take long for Jen to work out that this person she's writing to is
not Mr Chadwick, but when she stops writing, he drops all pretense immediately and introduces
himself as Eric.
Eric shows her an article from the local newspaper to explain.
Turns out, last Christmas he blew up at Moody during a holiday party, then flooded one of
the college buildings.
Moody got him expunged, and he ended up spending two months in a psychiatric hospital.
So Eric is in a bad place.
He claims that no other Straka researchers will touch him now, except for one guy in
Paris.
So with our two present-day main characters here, what do we know about this VMS mystery?
Well, in the foreword, we get some information through both Eric's notes to Jen and the
footnotes of Ship of Theseus itself, written by editor and translator FX Caldera.
FXC is just as mysterious as Straka.
Eric says that every serious scholar thinks the annotations in Ship of Theseus were written
by either a complete crank or VMS himself.
Neither figure gave public interviews, and FXC never translated for anyone else.
The FX is believed to stand for either Francesco or Philip Shibregas, depending on source,
according to Eric, but no one knows.
They are known to be Brazilian, and must have arrived in New York sometime between 1924
and 1929, based on the fact they translated the last 13 of Straka's novels.
They were seemingly the only employee of Straka's publisher Karsten Sons, and started
Wing Shoes Press after his death in order to publish Ship of Theseus.
They personally claim to have communicated with Straka only via letters and notes in
the margins of his manuscripts, i.e. they never met him, nor knew his identity.
After Straka's death, FXC is believed to have returned to Brazil and died in the 60s.
As for Straka himself, within the world of S, he is one of the most famous slash infamous
authors of the early 20th century.
Press linked him to rumors of sabotage, espionage, conspiracy, subversion, larceny, and assassination,
and were given a list of outlandish crimes he was accused of on page 11.
Although it would be easy to disregard Theseus' myth, leaked documents apparently show that
multiple governments did want Straka dead.
He hardly released any public statements, and said he believed the authorship controversy
was misguided, not to mention a pernicious threat to his safety, liberty, and peace of
mind.
While he wrote a letter criticising the film adaptation of his novel The Santana March,
included as the earliest insert in S, we get the impression he liked to write about the
exploitation of capitalism, surrealist or fantastical settings, and protagonists being
philosophically angsty, all of which feature in Ship of Theseus.
In terms of solid facts, his novels are written in many different languages, but Ship of Theseus
specifically was written in Czech, according to Caldera.
Eric does confirm in the forward notes that Desjardins 1982 proved Straka wasn't truly
polylingual and genuinely needed a translator, giving FXC some credibility.
One of the most important events FXC describes is their account of the 1946 Havana incident,
i.e. Straka's assumed death.
They apparently received a telegram in May 1946 from Straka, asking them to meet at the
Hotel San Sebastian in Havana so he could give them the manuscript for Ship of Theseus
chapter 10.
The message hinted that he could not write the final lines without the two of us discussing
them in person, which would indicate they did share a close relationship.
FXC arrived on 5th June and was told he was out, but at midnight they started to get worried
and so entered his room.
There they saw
Chairs splintered, a table overturned, holes and slashes in the plastered walls, clothing
strewn, a wandered typewriter upside down on the floor, blood on the windowsill, and
the window opened to a three-storey fall into an alley.
Below the window, two men in police uniforms, loading a blanket-rolled body into the back
of a truck and carting it away.
FXC didn't follow the truck, citing their own shock and grief, but afterwards managed
to collect themselves and some pages of the chapter 10 manuscript floating about the room.
The final chapter of Ship of Theseus novel is mostly constructed from these pages, with
the end written by FXC.
Eric hates that FXC never admitted which pages are Strachas, and some scholars theorise
they may have made up the account of his death entirely.
The other important thing FXC does in the foreword is give us a list of the most popular
Stracha candidates, but we're going to come back to that in the next video section.
Otherwise, that's the foreword.
Jen, Eric, Caldera and Stracha.
These are the four names we will be referencing a lot.
From now on, Jen and Eric write in three different colour combinations, blue and black, then
yellow and green, then purple and red.
We know this is the chronological order, because Jen and Eric will often add on to previous
notes.
So let's go through the remainder of the blue-black phase.
Jen soon starts to suspect that some of FXC's footnotes may exist to hide ciphers intended
for Stracha, so she dives into research and manages to discover previously unknown information
about FXC remarkably quickly.
This includes a name, Philomila Xabregas Caldera, making her not a man like most academics assumed.
Jen finds this via a manifest for a ship named Imperia, which had her down as a crew member
and translator on multiple trips between Brazil and New York in the 1920s.
Jump to November 1959, and this name is on another passenger manifest, from New York
back to São Paulo.
Besides these, there are virtually no traces.
She doesn't seem to have returned to the US, and Wingshoe's press was evicted for
non-payment in January 1960.
The only other record is her obituary, posted in Fioranova in 1964.
But this obituary is incredibly suspicious, because the only proof of death is a photo
of an unmarked headstone that the photographer claims is Caldera's.
So our peers start to wonder, is it possible that FXC could still be alive?
She would be over a hundred in their present, so it's unlikely, but she may at least have
lived past 1964.
Additionally, Jen is starting to suspect, based on Philomila's anecdotes, that she
and Straca may have been romantically involved, despite never meeting.
Going back to VMS, a couple of important events during his lifetime are mentioned here that
will become extremely relevant later.
Firstly, the Pre-Bouchard.
In September 1912, Straca was offered a prestigious literary prize that was sponsored by businessman
Hermes Bouchard.
But Straca refused the award, and infamously sent a tufted capuchin monkey to accept it
in his stead.
This act is essentially what started his whole anarchist wildcard reputation, and we'll
talk about it a lot more in the next section.
Secondly, Straca had an agent before FXC called Louis Luper.
Although maybe he didn't, because Luper completely disappeared in 1930.
However, in 1925, Luper auctioned off several of Straca's possessions, including 19 obsidian
pieces and a whistle with this S symbol carved on it.
Now, these artifacts were apparently from a, bear with me here, 17th century shipwreck
which buried a sailor called Archimedes de Sobrero.
Sobrero is another mysterious author who supposedly wrote a book called The Archer's
although most people think neither existed.
Until Jen finds proof that they did on page 21, and that's all we need to know for now.
Eric says most of these pieces and the whistle are currently kept in the Prague-Straca archive,
one of a few around the world.
The third important event to know about, or rather, events, is a series of 15-20 unsolved
murders occurring between the 1930s and 1970s.
Each of these involved an anonymous body washing ashore with no clear cause of death,
no ID, no fingerprints, and carrying a page from a Straca novel.
The first was found in 1936 in Santorini, Greece, and so we're going to refer to them
as the Santorini Man Deaths.
Throughout this, we continue to learn more about Jen and Eric as they start to open up
to each other.
Jen is in limbo at the moment, not knowing exactly what she wants to do with her life.
She just got dumped by her boyfriend of three years over email during spring break and doesn't
have many friends.
Her well-off dad has arranged a marketing job for her in New York, starting two months
after graduation.
She has to take it, but doesn't really want to.
The only thing she really likes is research, and she soon starts neglecting her coursework
in favour of reading Straca's books instead.
Eric, meanwhile, gives further details about his time at PSU.
Turns out he came there specifically to work with Moody, against advice.
Moody was always hard to please, but Eric trusted him until just before the Christmas
party disaster.
Since being in hospital, he has been frantically focused on work, neglecting to sleep and living
off almost nothing in a small place south of the tracks.
And he has been using steam tunnels to get around campus unseen, so again, not doing
very well.
In fact, Eric has also recently been in a bad relationship.
He admits on page 74 to having been involved with another of Moody's PhD students before
she betrayed him, a woman called Ilsa Dirks, who is a teaching assistant for one of Jen's
classes.
So our two scribblers bond over this mutual feeling of betrayal, and also being distant
from their families.
Eric doesn't have a great relationship with his parents, and doesn't explain why yet.
But Jen does explain.
She says her parents were very protective growing up, because once when she was seven
she wandered off and everyone thought she was kidnapped.
Their subsequent treatment of her as fragile influenced Jen's self-image, and there's
some mild resentment and emotional distance on both sides.
It's at this point in their bonding when Jen suggests the two actually meet up in person.
But Eric turns her down and then later doesn't show up.
Essentially, he's scared, because he clearly likes Jen and isn't great with people.
So there's a bit of back and forth for a while.
But thankfully not too much.
They both end up sweetly sharing their feelings on page 83, and from this point on they are
officially Jerrick.
But still no meetup.
Now that Eric trusts Jen, he reveals on page 64 what this whole Moody fight was about.
The Summersby tape.
This tape features a man called Victor M. Summersby, who is on the list of Straka suspects,
confessing to being VMS.
Eric tracked it down from the daughter of Summersby's lawyer, but after he returned, Moody got Ilsa
to steal it.
This is why Eric felt betrayed, and lashed out at Moody.
The tape was recorded in 1952, so after Havana, right before Summersby himself died by supposedly
falling off a ship.
However, at the tape's end there is a knock, followed by some unintelligible words.
So that's another suspicious death.
Eric gives Jen the transcript, but says that it isn't credible enough for him to go public,
and besides, he's starting to doubt Summersby's confession anyway.
So Eric is concerned about Moody and Ilsa finding out that Jen is now involved.
Again, Jen is in Ilsa's class.
On one occasion, Jen sees Moody and Ilsa together at a cafe called the Pronghorn Java, and has
to quickly hide her Straka novel.
She also sees Ilsa wearing one of Straka's obsidian pieces as a necklace, which is interesting
because the Prague Archive just reported a few of these missing.
The stakes are raised on page 74, because Jen is asked at work by Ilsa to provide a
list of everyone who has accessed the library archive.
Jen's name is all over these records, and so she tries to stall it first, but eventually
Ilsa emails her boss, and she has to send them.
Before she does, though, she sees that four unknown people have been inside the archive,
using VIP visitor cards.
Two went in with Ilsa and Moody, but two others went alone.
This ties in with several other unnerving occurrences around campus, suggesting that
Moody and Ilsa might not be the only ones here with an agenda.
Speaking of, at some point in this phase, Eric gets a cheque in the mailroom from something
called the Seren Institute, offering him funding.
Eric has never heard of this group, but they apparently saw him present a paper at a Straka
conference in Lisbon two years ago.
So he decides not to questions luck and takes the money.
That's all the blue-black notes, now it's time to move to the yellow-green.
This middle phase handily has more notes in the middle of the book, compared to the start
or end.
It also includes some of the biggest finds for Jen and Eric about VMS and the history
of this world, so we'll be coming back to those in part three.
Things are picking up in Pollard.
First off, Ilsa tells Jen she knows she is working with Eric, although Jen denies it.
Also, Moody is going to release his book in one month, giving Jen and Eric a ticking clock.
However, they are starting to question Summersby as Straka for a few reasons, not least because
Summersby claimed on the tape that he did his own translations, and they know FXC is
real now.
So since that is Moody's theory, they need to either prove him wrong or discredit him
by proving he got the tape unethically.
Also, more Straka artifacts are going missing, including the whistle that was in Prague.
Meanwhile, Jen is not doing well academics-wise because she has stopped attending classes.
She is totally disillusioned and feels like she has no purpose, warming up to the idea
of just running away to Paris with Eric and or going to grad school.
Worse than this though, she apparently has some kind of disciplinary hearing coming up
where she'll need to testify against Ilsa, but we don't know why.
Amidst all this, Jen wants to break into Moody's office and steal back the Summersby tape and
missing artifacts, but Eric thinks this will cause trouble and for a while she drops the
subject.
In a complete reversal, Eric is doing great, now he has money.
He makes three important trips during this phase.
The first is to New York for an auction, which has a photo of the Havana scene in 1946.
Afterwards, Eric mentions that Ilsa was there and also a mysterious agent bidding on behalf
of someone anonymous.
While there, he meets an important character, Jean Bernard Desjardins.
You might recall that Desjardins is an old Straka academic, he's that one guy in Paris
from the forward.
His main theory is that Straka was part of the S-Organisation, a secret writers' collective
with ties to political activism.
Desjardins was Moody's thesis advisor, but the two don't get along anymore.
Desjardins talks with Eric in New York, but afterwards ignores his calls, so Eric considers
going to Paris to try and meet him again with funding from Serin.
However, before he can, two things happen.
First, he receives a package containing documents, a note from Desjardins and one of the obsidian
pieces.
The letter, included as an insert on page 86, claims he is giving Eric these out of
fear for their security and he can't say more for safety reasons.
But the language of the letter is strange.
Eric says the English is less fluent than Desjardins seemed capable of.
Shortly after this, Desjardins suddenly dies.
He falls from the balcony of Hôtel des Deux Martres, so instead of going to Paris to meet
him, Eric attends his funeral with funding from Serin.
And what do you know, he reports back that no one who knew Desjardins believes he killed
himself.
Also, during the service someone sneaks Eric an invitation to a strange dinner with a bunch
of other scholars.
He can't tell whether they are connected to Serin and doesn't want to ask.
They certainly don't seem to trust Moody, but they also unsubtly talk up how committed
Desjardins was to sharing all his findings, which could insinuate much.
Another noteworthy thing is that Elsa is present at the funeral.
However, when Eric brags to her about his funding, which is stupid by the way, her reaction
suggests she might be there without Moody's knowledge.
Interesting.
The third trip is in April, when Eric decides to go to Brazil to find FXC.
Through multiple cryptic postcards, we track his journey between April 12th and 20th.
First, he finds Caldera's cousins in her hometown L'Ensoir, and they tell him she
came back but left again in the early 60s.
He follows more clues to reach a town called Maro, where shockingly enough, he finds Caldera
alive.
She has been hiding there for years under the name Ermalinda Pega.
A few people have been helping to protect and take care of her, including her main guy
named Arturo, but Eric says she was still very sharp mentally, enough to answer some
questions.
Unfortunately though, she maintains that the foreword was true and she never met Straca.
Eric describes Caldera as wistful when speaking of him, but ultimately, she has come to terms
with how it all ended.
When Eric tells her about how he and Jen have been using the book though, she is thrilled.
As he leaves, she wishes him luck and says, don't make the same mistake we did.
Before Brazil, Eric was in fact doing exactly that, and still refusing to meet up with Jen.
However, after having a heart to heart with himself, he writes her a letter on page 203
about his past.
This Eric backstory explains how he got into Straca in the first place.
It started when he was 16.
He was suffering from bad insomnia and depression and became distanced from religion.
His uncle Zeke took him on a boat trip up the coast to help, but Eric had a series of
panic attacks and ended up bailing half way after they had an argument.
While he was heading home alone, Zeke got into a wreck and died, and Eric's parents
blamed him.
But that day was when he first read Straca, so VMS is tied to the most difficult time
of his life.
Telling Jen all this seems to give Eric some catharsis and clarity, and he finally agrees
to meet at the Varsity Cinema right before leaving for Brazil.
However, Jen doesn't show this time because she's ill, leaving them without a way to
contact each other, hence the postcards.
After Eric returns, they both realise that Philomela was onto something, and Jen echoes
her sentiment, let's not make the same mistakes Philo and Straca did.
While Jen and Eric make these breakthroughs, the mysterious figures hanging around Pollard
start to act.
Jen has seen them three times, including during Elsa's class, and starts suspecting that
her mail has been tampered with.
An S symbol appears on the side of the Varsity, which neither Jen nor Eric put there.
At some point, someone follows Jen home from the library, prompting her to use the same
steam tunnels as Eric.
And then, on page 308, the pair discover that the Santorini Man deaths have begun again,
with one as recent as last October.
Things culminate when several fires occur near Jen.
This is first mentioned on page 128, and Eric thinks they might be diversions, but a bigger
fire is alluded to on page 258.
It seems as though at some point, there is a fire at a motel Jen is staying at while
scared to be in her apartment, and then another at her parents' barn while she is visiting.
The motel fires teased much earlier than the barn, so this series of events is pretty confusing
for a while, but Jen mentions on page 263 that while they were at the motel watching
the fire, there was a guy who kept looking at her.
She doesn't know whether he was involved, but it's because of him she went to her parents'
place, and she's worried that he followed her.
An S-symbol is visible on the barn wall after the fire, so this intimidation is clearly
targeted.
Okay, so we have some building tension stepping into the purple-red phase.
Just like the yellow-green phase takes up most of the middle of S, these are the most
prevalent colours in the later third.
The more romantic colours prove appropriate, as it's confirmed on page 248 that Jerec
finally meets.
This seems very sweet, and we get continuing anecdotes of them meeting on page 280 and
290.
The romance is flourishing.
However, this is interrupted briefly when Jen decides to reveal in another letter that
the whole story about her childhood disappearance earlier was actually a total lie.
The truth is a bit more complicated.
Turns out she deliberately disappeared during to feeling emotionally neglected by her parents
after her brother died.
The truth is a bit more complicated.
Turns out she deliberately disappeared due to feeling emotionally neglected by her parents
after her brother died, and spent several days hiding before giving herself up to the
police, alongside another runaway who helped her.
So both her and Jerec feel guilty.
This reframes her complicated relationship with her parents.
If she rebels against their wishes for her future now, she's choosing to run from them
again.
So she wonders whether it's worth it.
Jen apologises to Jerec for lying, but he's pretty understanding, and to be honest this
whole plot thread has very little impact on the book, besides giving Doris a reason to
include more inserts, so there's no need to remember any of it.
Eventually Jen decides to reject the job, and begs Jerec for them to leave Pollard together
away from the danger, again mirroring Straka and Caldera.
Running does seem reasonable when the trouble facing Jen and Jerec starts to build on multiple
fronts.
Lastly from the uni, we find out what Jen's hearing against Ilsa is about.
If reading is front to back, we learn on page 23 that Jen has been accused of something,
but it's not until 318 when Erik gives Jen a paper to use in Ilsa's class that we can
guess it's plagiarism.
Additionally, Jen gets fired from the library, which she suspects is because of one of the
people on the special collection logs.
Speaking of which, remember how Jen was tempted to break into Moody's office earlier?
Well, turns out that's back on the table.
Given everything else happening, you may be thinking, why would she do that?
And Erik agrees.
But Jen is fuelled by her righteous anger towards Moody stealing all these artefacts,
and so goes ahead and reports her findings on page 355.
Moody does indeed have one of the obsidian pieces, but not a physical copy of the Summersby
tape or the Archer's Tales, like Jen suspected.
Although she does see a schematic suggesting that Moody is preparing to store something
new in the library, it's unknown what exactly, but the design suggests the object is either
very valuable or very delicate.
Jen swears to Erik that she didn't take or move anything, but the next day campus cops
are all over Moody's office.
A little earlier, on page 317, a picture of Erik was in the Daily Pronghorn, and we don't
know why at the time, but it now seems that he's likely a suspect when he notes,
I told you it was a terrible idea.
It is confirmed that the police do come to Erik's apartment, but he refuses entry without
a warrant, as he should.
This worries Jen that whoever is following her will now target Erik, but he reckons if
they haven't done anything so far, then they probably won't.
Jen though is seeing the men frequently, including outside her apartment.
The pair have been switching the book location around, and this is partially because scary
phrases in Ship of Theseus start being underlined independently, suggesting someone else is
aware of their communications.
It's at this point that Jen finally suggests they ditch the book and switch to email or
something, but Erik is reluctant.
He says it's because he likes having it as a scrapbook of ideas, but this is just door
slam shading.
At this point they really shouldn't be writing notes if other people are reading them.
Still, they brainstorm where they can meet without being seen together.
Being watched though is nothing.
Officials confirm that the barn fire was indeed arson, and police are watching over Jen due
to the proliferation of incidents.
Erik still thinks this is someone being paid by Moody to scare them, but Jen is quite rightfully
terrified and angry.
What finally shakes Erik is receiving an ominous letter from Arturo in Brazil apologising
that they had to turn away his colleague because he made FXC uneasy.
This implies that someone was tracking Erik the entire time he was in Brazil, which is
insane.
Then on page 251, Erik hears someone calling his name in the steam tunnels and sprints.
Jen does not trust her flat anymore after she returns to find her window open despite
leaving it closed.
I was too afraid to go near it in case I got pushed like Desjardins.
Eventually it's too much, and after hearing someone in her apartment she decides to leave.
Erik offers her his place, but she's worried about leading the men to him.
This brings us to the third strand of trouble, Jen's family.
A month before she's supposed to graduate, after the fire, her parents announce a surprise
sudden visit.
She calls her sister to find out why, and is told that her ex, Jacob, got in touch with
them, claiming he was worried about how she was acting.
He told them all about Erik and her academic crash out, and if that wasn't enough, her
sister also snitched about how Jen had a lot of crazy s*** when she came home.
When her parents finally show, they think Erik caused the fire and she can't convince
them otherwise.
The situation escalates drastically and they try to take her to a psych facility, but thankfully
she manages to run.
So now Jen essentially has to go into hiding at Erik's place after her dorm gets cleared
out.
So far everything has been going terribly, until Erik decides to finally confront Elsa.
It's implied on page 383 that he visits her, and it actually helps.
Afterwards Elsa suddenly drops the plagiarism accusation against Jen.
Apparently Erik told Elsa that Jen didn't use his paper, which is actually true.
Jen says afterwards she buckled down and wrote it after all, but Erik didn't know that.
He just had faith.
The fact Elsa believes him though, shows a surprising level of trust on her part.
During this conversation they manage to talk through their baggage and reach some sort
of understanding.
This shows how Erik has changed too.
He says he wasn't as angry at her as he expected.
A lot of that has faded since meeting Jen.
So he tells Elsa that at the end of the day, all of them are just trying to figure out
what they want.
She in turn admits she really doesn't care about Moody and is only in this for herself.
While Erik is mending bridges with Elsa, Moody makes a surprising move and contacts
him.
It's worth mentioning that for a while now, Moody has been consistently seen drunk around
town.
He leaves notes in the pronghorn java, and then the steam tunnel is asking Erik to call
him, to which Erik eventually decides to leave a note in return.
Moody responds with a letter.
He doesn't accept much blame, but says that if Erik gives him legal consent to use the
tape, he'll gladly give him credit for finding it.
Erik realises that Summersbee's lawyer's daughter must have told Moody's publisher
she gave the tape to Erik, so now Moody can't publish his book without Erik signing off.
This means Erik finally has leverage.
If he can get a meeting with the publisher, he might be able to tell her about his and
Jen's discoveries and dismantle Moody's theory.
Jen and Erik at this point have their own theory about who Strachat is, which we'll
get to, and think they can convince the publisher to back them instead.
Also, note that in this phase, Erik has been getting more money from Seren alongside a
photo of the Havana incident, and Jen does not trust them, and suspects Erik will soon
be asked to repay it somehow.
As we reach the 400 page mark, a lot of elements in the Jerek storyline pay off in short succession.
Although this slightly abandons the non-chronological framework, it does help the book feel like
it's reaching some sort of climax.
Jen and Erik plan to fly abroad together the minute Jen is finished with Uni, and have
the Seren Institute cover the tickets.
Newly motivated, Jen manages to get her act together and nails the final, meaning she
can definitely graduate.
However, the night before her exam, Erik gets a letter and package from Arturo.
He wants to come round, but Jen thinks she already knows what the letter says and doesn't
want to hear it.
Sure enough, we learn on page 414 that Philomila has died in her sleep.
She leaves them a sweet letter wishing them both love, but the true surprise comes from
what's inside the package.
The missing pages of Ship Odysseus, Chapter 10.
In another surprising turn, Erik's meeting with publisher Esme Emerson Plum does not
go well.
She wasn't buying their theory at all and says they're going to publish Moody's book
with or without Erik's permission.
Erik decides that he can't leave without confronting Moody in person, so he does so
on page 419.
It's a contrast to how Ilsa acted.
Moody is drunk and laughs at Erik, both when he asks about the guys following Jen and then
about the publishing going ahead.
Jen, however, decides to email the university provost and tell them that Moody has tried
to bribe her for access to the archives.
This is a lie, obviously, but she hopes it will allow them to find the stolen artefacts
in his office.
She also emails back and forth with her father about the whole hospital incident, during
which he officially cuts her off financially.
But Jen thinks this is fair enough.
She now has other priorities.
It's directly after they work together against Moody that Erik tells Jen he loves her for
the first time.
Appropriate.
The climax of the purple-red phase occurs on page 453.
Since Jen and Erik are meeting in person now, we have to read between the lines to understand
events they were both present for.
But what seems to happen is this.
While meeting in a planetarium, the projector goes out, and suddenly an unknown man is there
with them.
They get into some sort of physical altercation before the pair manages to make a break for
it and they end up fleeing the country early with almost no belongings.
Who this man was exactly and whether Jen and Erik are safe remains pretty ambiguous.
And that's where this phase ends.
Now, there is a small epilogue phase, the double black, which does give us insight into
where Jen and Erik end up.
However, before we circle back around to that, we have a lot of things to explain first about
Layer 2, because we need to understand that to understand why Jen and Erik's story ends
the way it does.
So what have we covered so far?
Essentially, if someone was to only read the handwritten notes of S and only paid attention
to what Jen and Erik get up to, this is what they would get.
By itself, it's a pretty neat little story.
It has romance, academic drama, plenty of tension.
But a lot of things don't make sense yet.
The main confusion is probably how exactly did these stakes become so high?
This clearly goes beyond Moody and Elsa.
There are other forces at play here related to VMS and this mysterious S symbol.
Thus, our next section of video will dive into the important details we skipped over.
What exactly did Jen and Erik discover about VMStrakka and the history of this world?
And why did they seem to be getting targeted because of it?
Can we ourselves make sense of it all?
Let's try to answer the question, who is VMStrakka?